A Finding Aid to the Violet Oakley Papers, 1841-1981, in the Archives of American Art AAA.oaklviol
Archives of American Art
- Financial Material, 1874-1977; Series 5; 3.1 Linear feet Boxes 39-42
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1874-1910 (Box 41, Folder 16-29)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1911-1919 (Box 41, Folder 30-38)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1920-1922 (Box 41, Folder 39-46)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1923, January-April (Box 41, Folder 47-53)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1924, May-December (Box 42, Folder 1-4)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1925-1929 (Box 42, Folder 5-18)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1930-1936 (Box 42, Folder 19-30)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1937-1949 (Box 42, Folder 31-41)
  - Invoices/Receipts, 1950-1977 (Box 42, Folder 42-43)
- Artwork, 1883-1955; Series 6; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 42-43, 64, OV 67, OV 71
  Artwork includes architectural drawings and renderings; publication designs; a sketchbook; pencil sketches documenting travel, garden scenes, and portraits; prints; and a selection of works that are also cataloged in the card file. The series also includes Oakley family juvenilia, artwork by others, and miscellaneous drawings.
  - Architectural Drawings, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 44)
  - Architectural Drawings, Cogslea Garden, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 45)
  - Architectural Drawings, Gardens, 1906 (Box 42, Folder 46)
  - Book Illumination Designs, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 47)
  - Brochure and Letterhead Designs, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 48)
  - Preliminary Designs, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 49-51)
  - Drawings of Europe, circa 1890-1950 (Box 42, Folder 52-59)
  - Drawings of Europe, Coronation, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 60)
  - Landscape and Garden Sketches, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 61)
  - Portrait Sketches, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 62)
  - Prints, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 63)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1915-1955 (Box 42, Folder 64)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings, circa 1915-1955 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    Oversize material housed in Box 64, Folder 4.
  - Works Cataloged in Card File Stored Under "Financial Material", 1883-1884 (Box 43, Folder 2-3)
    Oversize material housed in OV 67.
  - Works Cataloged in Card File Stored Under "Financial Material", circa 1915-1955 (Box 43, Folder 4-5)
  - Drawings by Oakley Children, circa 1890-1920 (Box 43, Folder 6-7)
  - Cornelia Oakley's Drawings for Papa's [Pocket], circa 1890-1920 (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - By Others, circa 1915-1955 (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - By Others, Blueprints and Renderings, circa 1920-1950 (Box 43, Folder 10)
    Oversize materials housed in Box 64, Folder 5 and OV 71.
  - Oversize Miscellaneous Drawings from Box 43, Folder 1, circa 1915-1955 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Oversize Blueprints and Renderings by Others from Box 43, Folder 10, circa 1920-1950 (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Works Cataloged in Card File from Box 43, Folder 2, 1883 (Box OV 67)
  - Oversize Blueprints and Renderings by Others from Box 43, Folder 10, circa 1920-1950 (Box OV 71)
- Printed Material, 1866-1981; Series 7; 7.3 Linear feet Boxes 43-50, 65, OV 67
  Printed materials are of books, brochures, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, organizational reports and minutes, periodicals, programs, and reproductions of artwork by Oakley and others. These materials either relate directly to coverage of Oakley's artwork and career, or to her interests in the fields of politics, religion and spirituality, and philosophy.
  - Books, Children, 1873, 1906 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - Books, League of Nations, 1935-1937 (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - Books, Reports, 1911-1949 (Box 43, Folder 13-15)
    Includes reports for the Pennsylvania Sesquicentennial, Society of Mural Decorators and Painters, William Penn Memorial, and World Assembly for Moral Rearmament.
  - Books, Miscellaneous, 1943-1955 (Box 43, Folder 16)
    By Peter Howard and Alan Thornhill.
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, Violet Oakley (publication samples), 1906-1979 (Box 43, Folder 17)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, Violet Oakley (subscription mailings), circa 1920-1950 (Box 43, Folder 18-19)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, Violet Oakley (subscription mailings), 1920-1973 (Box 43, Folder 20-24)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (businesses, art supplies), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 25-26)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (businesses, booksellers), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 27)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (businesses, garden suppliers), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 28)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (businesses, international), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 29)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (businesses, United States), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 30)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (instruction and classes), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 31)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (lectures), circa 1900-1960 (Box 43, Folder 32)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (Pennsylvania capitol), circa 1920-1960 (Box 43, Folder 33)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (philosophy, politics, and religion), circa 1900-1960 (Box 44, Folder 1-2)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (miscellaneous), circa 1900-1960 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1873-1929 (Box 44, Folder 4-15)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1930-1953 (Box 44, Folder 16-25)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1954-1979 (Box 45, Folder 1-2)
  - Clippings, circa 1900-1980 (Box 45, Folder 3-13)
  - Clippings, 1896-1929 (Box 45, Folder 14-27)
  - Clippings, 1930-1945 (Box 45, Folder 28-40)
  - Clippings, 1946-1950 (Box 45, Folder 41-45)
  - Clippings, 1951-1964 (Box 46, Folder 1-7)
  - Clippings, 1961-1980 (Box 46, Folder 8-16)
  - Clippings, Artwork for Periodicals, 1939-1950 (Box 46, Folder 17)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, Grandma's Book for Little Margaret (Cornelia Oakley), circa 1900-1920 (Box 46, Folder 18)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, Mounted by C.G. Nicholson, 1926 (Box 46, Folder 19)
  - Clippings Scrapbook, Poems and Articles, 1953-1954 (Box 46, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1900-1955 (Box 46, Folder 21-22)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1901-1929 (Box 46, Folder 23-30)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930-1939 (Box 47, Folder 1-8)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1979 (Box 47, Folder 9-16)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, By Others, 1916-1979 (Box 47, Folder 17-25)
  - Exhibition Labels, circa 1900-1955 (Box 47, Folder 26)
  - Organizations, Annual Reports, 1915-1948 (Box 47, Folder 27-31)
  - Organizations, Annual Reports, 1950-1978 (Box 48, Folder 1-2)
  - Organizations, Constitutions and By-Laws, circa 1920-1960 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Organizations, Constitutions and By-Laws, 1895-1971 (Box 48, Folder 4-6)
  - Organizations, Minutes, circa 1920-1960 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Organizations, Minutes, 1931-1972 (Box 48, Folder 8-13)
  - Periodicals, with Artwork by Violet Oakley, 1922-1952 (Box 48, Folder 14)
  - Periodicals, 1866-1932 (Box 48, Folder 15-23)
  - Periodicals, 1933-1954 (Box 48, Folder 24-32)
  - Periodicals, 1955-1979 (Box 49, Folder 1-4)
  - Postcards, circa 1920-1960 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Posters, circa 1920-1955 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 1 and OV 67.
  - Programs, circa 1920-1960 (Box 49, Folder 7-8)
  - Programs, 1891-1935 (Box 49, Folder 9-22)
  - Programs, 1936-1959 (Box 49, Folder 23-33)
  - Programs, 1960-1979 (Box 50, Folder 1-3)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Violet Oakley, 1927-1934 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 2 and OV 67.
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, circa 1920-1960 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 3.
  - Travel Related, circa 1888-1949 (Box 50, Folder 6-9)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1920-1960 (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Oversize Posters from Box 49, Folder 6, circa 1920-1955 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Reproductions of Artwork by Oakley from Box 50, Folder 4, 1927-1934 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Oversize Reproductions of Artwork by Others from Box 50, Folder 5, circa 1920-1960 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Oversize Posters from Box 49, Folder 6, circa 1920-1955 (Box OV 67)
  - Oversize Reproductions of Artwork by Oakley from Box 50, Folder 4, 1927-1934 (Box OV 67)
- Photographs, 1890-1980; Series 8; 5.3 Linear feet Boxes 50-57, 65, OV 68
  Materials are organized by document type and subject. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  Photographs include albums, photographs, and negatives depicting Oakley, views of Cogslea, her family and friends, travel, exhibition events, and of her studio and works of art. Individuals of note include Edith Emerson, Elizabeth Shippen Green, Jessie Willcox Smith. Among the photographers are Elizabeth Buehrmann, Helen Dodd, J. M. Elliot, Haeseler, Philadelphia, Clayton Stone Harris, T. S. Jamison, Florence Maynard, Olive M. Potts, Eva Watson Schutze, and Mathilde Weil.
  - Album II, circa 1890-1929 (Box 50, Folder 11-15)
  - Album III, circa 1930-1960 (Box 50, Folder 16)
  - Album IV, circa 1940-1960 (Box 50, Folder 17-19)
  - Photographs of Violet Oakley, circa 1900-1960 (Box 50, Folder 20-21)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 4.
  - Photographs of Violet Oakley in Studio, circa 1900-1960 (Box 50, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Violet Oakley with Friends and Family, circa 1900-1950 (Box 50, Folder 23-26)
  - Photographs of Family, Arthur and Cornelia Oakley, circa 1898 (Box 50, Folder 27)
  - Photographs of Family, Hester Oakley Ward and Baby Margaret, circa 1900 (Box 50, Folder 28-29)
  - Photographs of Friends, Edith Emerson, circa 1954-1979 (Box 50, Folder 30)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 5.
  - Photographs of Friends, Frere-Smith Family, circa 1920-1950 (Box 50, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Friends, Elizabeth Shippen Green, circa 1911-1940 (Box 50, Folder 32-33)
  - Photographs of Friends, Jessie Willcox Smith, circa 1890-1925 (Box 51, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs of Friends, Ruth St. Denis, 1955-1964 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Friends, Thayer (baby), circa 1900-1930 (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Friends, circa 1920-1950 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    From envelope "What a beautiful place to live."
  - Photographs of Friends, circa 1895-1975 (Box 51, Folder 6-12)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 5 and OV 68.
  - Photographs of Cogslea Estate, Exterior, circa 1900-1972 (Box 51, Folder 13-21)
  - Photographs of Cogslea Estate, Interior, circa 1900-1940 (Box 51, Folder 22-23)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Houses, circa 1900-1950 (Box 51, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Events, Art Related (exhibition, Bulletin Building, PA), circa 1940-1955 (Box 51, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Events, Art Related (exhibition, Corcoran), 1930 (Box 51, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs of Events, Art Related (exhibitions, miscellaneous), 1943-1974 (Box 51, Folder 28)
  - Photographs of Events, Philadelphia Award, 1921 (Box 51, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Events, Westchester County Pageant, 1909 (Box 51, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Travel, Bermuda, 1964 (Box 51, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Travel, France, circa 1920-1936 (Box 51, Folder 32-33)
  - Photographs of Travel, Gibraltar, circa 1910-1930 (Box 51, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Travel, Great Britain, circa 1920-1940 (Box 51, Folder 35)
  - Photographs of Travel, Italy, circa 1910-1930 (Box 51, Folder 36-38)
  - Photographs of Travel, Low Countries and Switzerland, circa 1936-1949 (Box 51, Folder 39)
  - Photographs of Travel, Panama, 1914 (Box 51, Folder 40)
  - Photographs of Travel, United States, circa 1920-1970 (Box 51, Folder 41)
  - Photographs of Travel, Miscellaneous, circa 1910-1950 (Box 51, Folder 42)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, All Angels Church Stained Glass Windows, circa 1900 (Box 51, Folder 43)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Army and Navy Triptychs, 1941-1942 (Box 51, Folder 44)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, "Building of the House of Wisdom" (Charlton Yarnall house), circa 1910 (Box 51, Folder 45)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, "Constitutional Convention" (Cuyahoga County Courthouse), circa 1911 (Box 51, Folder 46)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 6 and OV 68.
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Christ at Geneva, circa 1937 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, "Dante's Window", circa 1911 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Great Women of the Bible, circa 1945 (Box 52, Folder 3-4)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 6.
  - Photographs of Works of Art, "Great Wonder", circa 1924 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, "Life of Moses", circa 1928 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 7.
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Pennsylvania Capitol Murals (Governor's reception room), circa 1906 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    Oversize material housed in OV 68.
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Pennsylvania Capitol Murals (Senate chamber), 1926 (Box 52, Folder 8-9)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Pennsylvania Capitol Murals (Supreme Court), 1926 (Box 52, Folder 10-11)
    Oversize material housed in Box 65, Folder 7 and OV 68.
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Triptychs, circa 1940-1955 (Box 52, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Miscellaneous, circa 1920-1950 (Box 52, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Miscellaneous Models, circa 1920-1950 (Box 52, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Sculpture, 1955 (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Sketches and Projects, circa 1920-1950 (Box 52, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Sketches of Men, circa 1920-1950 (Box 52, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, Sketches of Women, circa 1920-1950 (Box 52, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, By Others, circa 1925-1961 (Box 52, Folder 19-20)
  - Negatives, "Violet and Jessie and Someone Else", circa 1900-1950 (Box 52, Folder 21)
  - Negatives of Cogslea Estate, circa 1900-1950 (Box 52, Folder 22-24)
  - Negatives of Children, circa 1900-1950 (Box 52, Folder 25-33)
    Includes women and men.
  - Negatives of Women, circa 1900-1950 (Box 52, Folder 34-45)
    Includes children and men.
  - Negatives of Works of Art, circa 1900-1950 (Box 52, Folder 58-61)
  - Negatives, Chronological, 1949 (Box 52, Folder 62-64)
  - Negatives, Chronological, 1952-1954 (Box 53, Folder 1-14)
  - Negatives, Chronological, 1955-1957 (Box 53, Folder 15-24)
  - Negatives, Chronological, 1958-1959 (Box 53, Folder 25-33)
  - Negatives, Chronological, 1960-1965 (Box 53, Folder 34-47)
  - Negatives, Chronological, 1966-1970 (Box 53, Folder 48-61)
  - Negatives, From Glass Plates, circa 1900-1930, circa 1970-1980 (Box 53, Folder 62)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1890-1910; 322 Glass negatives (Box 54-57)
  - Oversize Photographs of Oakley from Box 50, Folder 20, circa 1900-1960 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Oversize Photographs of E. Emerson and E.S. Green from Box 50, Folder 30 and 32, circa 1911-1930 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Photographs of J.W. Smith, R. St. Denis, and Friends from Box 51, Folder 1, 3, and 11, circa 1890-1964 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Photographs of "Constitutional Convention" and Great Women of the Bible from Box 51, Folder 46 and Box 52, Folder 3, circa 1911-1945 (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Photographs of "Life of Moses" and Pa. Capitol Murals from Box 52, Folder 6, 8, and 10, circa 1926-1928 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Oversize Photographs of Friends from Box 51, Folder 11, circa 1920-1929 (Box OV 68)
  - Oversize Photographs of "Constitutional Convention" from Box 51, Folder 46, circa 1911 (Box OV 68)
  - Oversize Photographs of Pa. Capitol Murals and Triptychs from Box 52, Folder 7, 10, and 12, circa 1906-1955 (Box OV 68)